HEMANT GUSAIN

221/16, Kasampur, Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, 250001 someshgusain@gmail.com | +919557573847 https://www.linkedin.com/in/hemant-gusain-b1613b131

Exceptionally communicative, energetic & result oriented professional with 4+ years' experience and proven knowledge of Application development, database, scripting languages and real time data. Seeks an opportunity to further build a strong skills set while working on multiple projects & highly interested in a role with a company that promotes best practices and offers a wealth of customer projects.

EXPERIENCE

01/08/2022 - PRESENT

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER – L2, GEMINI SOLUTIONS (GURUGRAM)

- Carry out training on development and deployment cycle for trainees.
- Migrating training data with new computations and new requirement for ML model.

30/11/2020 - 29/07/2022

SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, ALGOSCALE TECHNOLOGIES INC. (NOIDA)

- Analyze all issues of external clients and provide effective resolutions for the same.
- Work with developers to design algorithms and flowcharts.
- Produce clean, efficient code based on specifications.
- Integrate software components and third-party programs.
- Verify and deploy programs and systems.
- Developing back-end components to improve responsiveness and overall performance.

17/09/2019 - 27/11/2020

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, FOURBRICK TECHNOLOGY OPC PVT. LTD. (NOIDA)

- Provided solutions by analyzing requirements and designing, developing and implementing software applications for multiple websites.
- Use various techs including ML to make repairs and optimize the corporate website.
- Troubleshoot the existing application to get accurate results after Alpha & Beta testing.
- Represented team at meetings with executives, discuss project & milestones.
- Researched new techniques and implemented backend for delivering a project.

06/08/2018 - 13/09/2019

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, INDIAN HOSPITALITY (NEW DELHI)

- Researching, designing, implementing and managing software programs.
- Identifying areas for modification in existing programs and subsequently developing these modifications.
- Determining operational practicality.
- Create technical documentation for reference and reporting.
- Determining operational practicality.
- Writing and implementing efficient code

IT SKILLS

- Highly efficient in **Python Programming**.
- Resourceful in the Django Rest framework.
- Have good hands on in MySQL & PostgreSQL.
- Good Knowledge of FLASK, REDIS and ML.
- Get in touch with MongoDB & AWS Chalice.

- Friendly with **Linux OS** environment.
- Skilled in prime AWS Services.
- Handled **Gunicorn** server with **Nginx**.
- Aware with **Deep Learning** concepts.
- Understanding of Angular and HTML.

EDUCATION

AUGUST 2013 - JULY 2017

B.TECH, BHARAT INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, MEERUT

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering

DR. A.P.J. ABDUL KALAM TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY UTTAR PRADESH

PROJECTS

PARSPEC (parspec.io)

Role and Technologies - Designed Django Backend, Search Server (Django RQ), used PyPDF2

- The solution enables all stakeholders in the construction supply chain to optimize the buying and selling of materials especially lighting products.
- It does so by applying computer vision to parse data from designers' specs, triggering an AI-informed web crawler of OEM tear sheets using **Redis-Queue** to identify the best matches, providing strategic recommendations.
- Ultimately, this will reduce bid preparation time by 75%, cutting the cost of
 acquisition and, more importantly, increasing the amount of bids that can be
 processed by the same staff to generate more sales with even better service.

ASSUREX

Role and Technologies - Deployed on Flask, Used KNN to get most appropriate Category for Data

- Helps in categorizing the Training Data into suitable bracket on Input to the application.
- Basic aim of Assurex is to make hierarchy of activities, products and components which leads to better training and assignments.

SALESDOCS

Role and Technologies – Designed Django backend with multiple tenants via PostgreSQL schemas

- It is the first and the only SaaS based productivity software dedicated to Pre-Sales Engineers.
- Start efficiently tracking your work, building your client relationships, and highlighting your contributions to close contracts in one application.
- It offers built-in reporting features that showcase your contribution to revenue as sales engineer.
- With salesdocs you have all information you need for planning and problem solving right at your fingertips with organized & up-to-date account information.

FANDOM LIVE

Role and Technologies - Map out Backend on Python Flask & Worked on Rest APIs

- Fandom.Live is the world first crowdsourcing platform that revolutionizes the traditional live entertainment industry through fan-centric innovation.
- There are fans from all over the world that want the chance to see a certain event or entertainer so at Fandom Live we provide that opportunity to all fans.

SMART ICU

Role and Technologies - Designed Backend on Flask & Done Face-Unlock using DLib library

- For real time tracking of patients. It has record of health parameters like Spo2, BP and Sugar. It has feature of readmission, maintain intake, treatments of patients.
- Doctor's also have notes of medicines given to patients and Nurse can also assign multiple doctor for patients based on his allergies described at time of registration.

MED AMBULANCE

Role and Technologies - Designed Backend in Flask & used mqtt to track the live location

- Equivalent to OLA & Uber. In this, user can book ambulance and responder. Admin can create hospital admin so that hospital can see real-tracking of ambulance & responder.
- It also includes real tracking of ambulance & responder on User-side application, driver side application and Hospital side application.

PENDLER

Role and Technologies - Worked on Django to Improve Backend Design

- Pendler is a Danish word which means Commuter. Commuting is periodically recurring travel between one's place of residence, work, or study, and exceeds the boundary.
- It helps grouping people and commuting together on fixed routes which reduces congestion on roads, CO2 emissions and saves time and efforts.

OYO DRF

Role and Technologies - Applied Numpy Arrays operation and Designed backend in Flask

- Oyo Rooms (stylized as OYO), also known as Oyo Hotels & Homes. It is one of the largest and fastest-growing hospitality chains of Hotels.
- The startup expanded globally with purchase of profitable properties on definite terms.

WIKIPEDIA SUMMARIZER

Role and Technologies - Applied Natural Language Processing (NLP) & used Gensim library

- Wikipedia is encyclopedia i.e. contains the vast knowledge of numerous content.
- Our motive is to view the huge amount of data in limited lines based on the search & automate the system.

IMAGE CLASSIFICATION

Role and Technologies - Used Deep Learning & train Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) Model

- Online world is in a rush. Today almost everything is bought or sold over the Internet. As the market is going online and orders are getting vast.
- It's hard to keep track of the variety & quality of products especially spices. So, we are making the system automatic to classify the variety & quality of organic products.

DIGIT RECOGNITION

Role and Technologies - Used Support Vector Machines (SVM) to train the model

- With the increase in consumption of goods & facilities, but lack of heavy & modern machineries in many remote areas to keep track of them, there is a need of Centralized place to keep record under a Network of agencies.
- In this Vendors will upload there hand written bills and receipt to a centralized application and those will get converted into digital or computer understandable form.

FACE AND EYE DETECTION

Role and Technologies - Used Haar Cascade xml files and OpenCV Library to detect

- Working on Machines & Systems in large scale needs the surety of working to meet the requirements of the production. Our Aim is to tackle this problem.
- We can keep the record time with tracking the worker's face & eyes on the machine.

SPEECH TO TEXT

Role with Technologies - Used speech recognition and pyttsx 3 module to convert

- Speech recognition is an important feature in several applications used such as home automation, artificial intelligence, etc.
- This project aims to provide a connection between the user on the application and the Pre-processed Database to quickly get the information about the requirements of User.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Received several client appreciations for suggesting new approach for defect fix and identifying and rectifying loopholes in existing design.
- Received client and Higher Managements appreciation for On-time defect free project completion.
- Regularly organized and given knowledge transfer sessions on business and technical things to fresher.

TRAINING & CERTIFICATION

- PYTHON FOR DATA SCIENCE from IBM on 27.06.2020.
- PYTHON (BASICS) from HACKERRANK on 18.06.2020.
- APPLIED MACHINE LEARNING from APPLIED AI COURSE in 2020.